This video is supported by Keeps.
在2021年初 太空叉执行了一次独一无二的破纪录的发射
At the beginning of 2021, SpaceX pulled off a unique mission that broke records.
火箭把人类的骨灰送入了近地轨道
Onboard were human ashes which were travelling to lower Earth orbit.
这项服务是由Celestis推出的
This service was arranged by the company Celestis
你甚至可以找他们 只花12500美元 就能把骨灰送上月球
and they even offer to send ashes to the Moon for just $12,500,
可比太空旅行便宜多了~
which is cheap in terms of spaceflight.
但这并不是这次发射任务中最值得关注的一点
But this wasn't the most impressive part of the mission.
本次任务一共发射了143颗卫星入轨
In total, this mission launched 143 satellites into orbit,
打破了之前印度创造的一箭104星的记录
breaking the previous record of 104, set by India.
这是太空叉最新的一项服务 名为“顺风车”
This is part of a new service that SpaceX now offers called 'Rideshare'
可以让小型卫星搭其他卫星的“便车”
which allows smaller satellites to hitch a ride with other satellites, drastically reducing the cost.
在80年代 如果你有一颗500公斤的卫星想送进地球轨道
If you had a 500kg satellite in the 80's and wanted to launch it into Earth's orbit,
那你的选择可真的不多
you didn't have a lot of options.
那年代可没有这么便宜的可复用火箭
Back then, there were no cheap reusable rockets.
所以身为卫星主人的你
So as the owner of the satellite,
得支付整枚火箭制造与发射的所有成本
you had to pay for the entire cost of building the rocket plus all of the launch costs.
直到最近几年之前
Up until fairly recently,
卫星也一直是又大又笨重的 功能单一的东西
satellites have typically been large, bulky objects only capable of doing one thing.
别忘了 我们现在兜里揣的手机上面的技术
You have to remember that the technology we have in our pockets
放到六七十年代要占满好几间屋子
used to take up entire rooms back in the 60's and 70's.
但这也只是一部分原因
But that's only part of the puzzle.
不但是当时的科技水平让卫星很大
Not only was the technology extremely oversized,
而且建造一个有足够保护 能抵御外太空恶劣环境的卫星
building a satellite that had enough protection to survive the harsh conditions of outer space
也让其变得很大
made them even bigger.
我们现在可以把卫星做得更小 更便宜
We can now make satellites much smaller and for a fraction of the cost.
因此 随着卫星越做越小 加之火箭发射成本也越来越低
So with satellites getting smaller and rocket launches getting cheaper,
一个新生行业正在以难以置信的速度发展——微小卫星行业
it has allowed a new industry to grow at an incredible rate: the small satellite industry.
小卫星的重量一般在五百公斤以下
Small sats are typically considered anything under 500kg.
而其中最火的是50公斤以下的那些
But it's those under 50kg that have become the most popular.
它们通常也叫作“纳卫星”
These are known as nanosatellites.
其中最成功的款式当属“立方卫星”
One of the most successful being the CubeSat.
它们是十厘米见方的科研卫星
These are small research satellites made up of 10cm modules.
高度可客制化 能让各家单位在太空进行科学研究
These are highly customizable and allow companies to perform research in space
比用传统卫星要便宜得多
that would otherwise be far too expensive.
它们通常会被带到国际空间站上 从那里部署
They are often carried up to the International Space Station and deployed from there
要么是从适配器上吐出去 要么是太空行走扔出去
using a deployer or literally being thrown by the astronauts during a space walk.
这可比扔棒球的速度快多了
That's much faster than any baseball pitch.
过去十年 立方卫星的数量急剧增长
Over the last decade, the number of these CubeSats being launched has increased dramatically
而它们的热度也一直在涨
and their popularity is set to grow even further.
由于价格低廉 这些卫星也抛弃了传统政府的公家火箭
With incredibly low prices, satellites have moved away from traditional government rockets
转而投靠便宜又《可靠》的SpaceX
in favour of the cheap and reliable SpaceX.
但近年来 大型通信卫星的订单量实际上已经有所下降
But in recent years, the amount of orders for big communication satellites has actually dropped
太空叉能给客户往太空射的东西已经越来越少了
and SpaceX have had less customers to launch into space.
与此同时 民营航天新秀火箭实验室的发射计划也在不断增加
Meanwhile, the new kid in town 'Rocketlab' has had an ever growing launch schedule.
他们的火箭更小更便宜
With a much smaller and cheaper rocket,
发射成本只有太空叉的一小部分
they can provide dedicated launches for a fraction of SpaceX's cost.
虽然猎鹰九号火箭发射成本已经很低了
Although the cost for each Falcon 9 is relatively cheap,
但每次发射还是要至少五千万美元
it will still set you back at least $50 million for a single launch.
如果你只发射一颗小卫星 那这还是贵的离谱
This option is completely over the top if you're only launching a small satellite.
而火箭实验室那边射一次只收七百万美元
Rocketlab on the other hand charges just $7 million per launch.
这让火箭实验室在方兴未艾的小卫星市场里脱颖而出
This has allowed Rocketlab to flourish with the rise of the small sat market.
因此 为了追上竞争者的脚步 太空叉开始了他们的“顺风车”企划
And so, in order to keep up with its competitors, SpaceX started their rideshare program.
大致思路是提供多个载重200公斤的载荷位 让大家平摊发射成本
The idea is to offer 200kg slots on the Falcon 9 in order to share the launch cost.
每200公斤只要一百万美元 比火箭实验室便宜得多
Each 200kg slot can be purchased for just $1 million, much cheaper than Rocketlab's Electron rocket.
等一等 先别急着下单！
But it gets even better.
如果你想发射一个更小的卫星
If you are launching a much smaller satellite
不想付全款？那就不付！
and don't want to pay the full price, you don't have to.
当卫星公司购买了猎鹰九号上一个载荷位
When a satellite company buys a slot on the Falcon 9,
他们可以选择和其它更小的卫星共用这一个载荷位
they can choose to share their slot with even smaller satellites,
即“顺风车的顺风车”
essentially creating rideshare within the rideshare.
Spaceflight Inc就是这样的一个卫星公司
One of these companies is Spaceflight Inc,
猎鹰九号上一个立方卫星载荷位 不要五千万 不要一百万 只要十五万！
which offers cubesat slots on the Falcon 9 for as little as $150,000.
虽然以前也有过这样的“顺风车”任务
Although rideshare missions have been done before,
但从来没达到这样的程度 这样低廉的价格
they have never been done on this scale and for such a low price.
太空叉不但让去太空的花销变得更加低廉
Not only is SpaceX making space more affordable,
他们还让这件事变得像叫嘀嘀打车一样简单方便
they are making it more accessible than ever with an Uber-like booking system.
首先上官网 选中你的卫星想去的轨道
First, you select the desired orbit of your satellite,
填好重量 然后从计划发射的列表中选择一个
the mass and then choose from one of the scheduled flights.
然后你要指定你的卫星要怎样适配到火箭上
Then you have to specify how your satellite will fit onto the rocket.
因为到时候火箭上会有非常多的不同的卫星
Since many different satellites will be onboard the rocket,
所以太空叉为此设计了一款标准载荷适配器 简化了卫星与火箭的连接
SpaceX has designed a standard payload adapter that simplifies how each satellite connects to the rocket.
之后 你可以选择一些其他附加服务 比如分离系统 供电系统
After that, you can choose extra addons like separation systems, electrical supplies
还有卫星燃料补加服务
and additional fuel for your satellite.
一切都选好后 应该要至少一百万美元
Once you have selected everything you need, it should cost you at least $1 million.
太空叉要求立即支付五千美元的定金
SpaceX requires a $5000 deposit immediately,
剩余款项分两期支付
with the rest of the payment being paid in two large installments.
虽然看起来还是非常贵
So although it's still incredibly expensive,
但这已经是目前把卫星发射入轨的便宜的方案了
it's by far the most cost effective way of getting satellites into orbit.
多亏了猎鹰九号惊人的复用能力
Thanks to the Falcon 9's incredible reusability,
太空叉能轻松在价格上打败竞争对手 且仍能保持盈利
SpaceX can comfortably undercut their competitors and still make a large profit.
但他们的顺风车计划还有更深远的打算
But their rideshare program goes even deeper than that.
尽管以往的大型卫星客户在减少
Despite the decline in typical large satellite customers,
太空叉的发射节奏却在加快
SpaceX's overall launch cadence has increased drastically.
如今他们绝大多数发射都是服务于自家的Starlink星座
Most of their launches are now dedicated to launching their very own Starlink satellites.
当Starlink完全部署后
When fully operational,
整个星座将有上万颗卫星环绕地球运行
this massive constellation will consist of 10's of thousands satellites orbiting the Earth.
将为包括最偏远的农村地区在内的全球几乎每一个地方提供高速互联网
This constellation will provide high speed internet to almost every part of the globe,
including the most rural areas.
也许太空叉最被忽视的成就之一
Perhaps one of SpaceX's most overlooked achievements
就是他们能以如此低的成本大规模生产这些卫星
is their ability to mass produce these satellites at such a low cost.
每颗卫星估值25万美元
Each satellite is estimated to cost around $250,000,
比传统卫星动辄数百万的价格便宜多了
extremely low compared to typical satellites which can easily cost millions of dollars.
每次发射60颗
With 60 satellites on each launch,
发射一次Starlink 总价大概在4500万美元
it brings the total cost for each Starlink launch to around $45 million.
想要发射上千颗卫星
With the plan to launch thousands of these satellites,
想要让星座完全可运行 发射总成本应该会很高
the cost to get their constellation fully operational will be enormous.
也因此 “顺风车”企划来了
But that's where the rideshare program comes in.
在该企划第一次正式发射的时候
During their first official rideshare launch,
载荷舱里硬塞了10个太空叉的Starlink卫星
SpaceX squeezed 10 Starlink satellites into the payload bay.
数量比通常一次发射的量要少
It may be less starlink satellites than they would usually launch,
但这次相当于有人给掏路费呀~
but it essentially gave them a free ride into space
因为其他卫星客户都是交了钱的
since the other customers were paying for the launch costs.
展望未来 太空叉很可能会让每一次顺风车任务中都拿Starlink卫星填空座
Going ahead, SpaceX will more than likely include Starlink satellites on all of their rideshare missions.
但太空叉的顺风车企划又是怎样影响到火箭实验室的？
But how does SpaceX's rideshare program affect Rocket Lab?
尽管太空叉和火箭实验室市场上有所重叠 但并没有真正从他们那里夺走多少
Despite eating directly into Rocktelab's market, it hasn't really taken much away from them.
其中一个问题是顺风车中所有卫星几乎都要去相同的轨道
One issue with ridesharing is that all satellites are essentially going to the same orbit.
所以想要让顺风车成团
So in order for a rideshare mission to happen,
所有卫星都得等客上满才能出发
all of the satellites need to wait until the rocket is at full capacity.
在每一个卫星都有各自严格时间规划的情况下 就会有问题
In a world where each satellite has its own strict schedule, this is a problem.
如果客户发现自己竟然要等这么久 那他们很可能转而寻找别的火箭发射
If a customer has to wait for too long, they will probably find a different rocket to launch on.
火箭实验室每次发射只为一个客户服务 收费会略高
Rocket Lab offers a dedicated launch to single customers for a slightly higher cost.
而他们现在也开始搞火箭回收了
But with Rocketlab now working towards reusing their rocket,
那他们相比太空叉就会有更高的价格竞争力
their prices could start to compete with SpaceX even more.
而正是这样的竞争 推动了太空飞行的成本大幅度下降
It's competition like this that will continue to drive the cost of spaceflight down massively.
等以后太空叉有了Starship这款完全可复用火箭
In the future though, SpaceX will have Starship - a fully reusable rocket
其有效载荷能力在当下一绝群雄
with a payload capability that overshadows anything that is around today.
有了它 一次发射不再是之前的60颗Starlink卫星
To put it into perspective, instead of launching 60 Starlink satellites on one launch,
而是240颗！
Starship could launch 240!
而其低到只有两百万美元的发射成本
And with the launch costs estimated to be just around $2 million,
更是让未来的顺风车任务有着无尽的发展前景
the opportunity for future rideshare missions seems endless.
到那时 Starship上的顺风车任务
With a full rideshare mission aboard Starship,
我们可能看到200公斤的载荷位不要一百万 只要五千块！
we could see the cost per 200kg slot lower from $1 million to $5,000.
但最终 所有这些都是为了实现太空叉的主要目标——送人类去火星
But in the end, all of this goes towards SpaceX's main goal of taking humans to Mars.
太空叉一路走来获得的每一分钱和技术进步都将实现其雄心勃勃的目标
Every bit of money and technical advancement that SpaceX picks up along the way
will help them in their ambitious quest.
太空叉能一路走到今天 马一龙真的很不容易
The journey for SpaceX has been long and hard for Elon Musk.
甚至在他刚创办太空叉的时候 他的头发就已经掉得差不多了
Even getting to the point of starting SpaceX took a lot out on his hairline.
后面工商就不翻了 不过你既然来看这个视频 那我觉得你可以了解一下
那么有没有一款………………
But did you know that 2 out of 3 guys will experience some kind of baldness by the time they're 35?
The best way to prevent this is by doing something about it while you still have hair left -
that's where Keeps comes in.
Keeps is an online subscription service that makes it easier and more affordable for men to treat male pattern baldness.
With a quick online doctor consultation,
Keeps will recommend the right treatment and ship it to your door every 3 months.
With FDA-approved hair loss medications, Keeps is effective and affordable.
It can take up to 6 months for the results to show, so it's important to act fast
and start taking care of your hair today!
If you'd like to support Primal Space and try out Keeps, visit keeps.com/primalspace
to receive 50% off your first order, that's keeps.com/primalspace.
如果您想支持本频道 欢迎去Patreon赞助
If you'd like to support the channel even more, consider becoming a Patron
可以让你名字出现在结尾名单 还可以拉你进Discord群
where you can give your input on each video and get exclusive access to our Discord server.
感谢大家观看 我们下期视频见
Thank you very much for watching and I'll see you in the next video.